- 荷尔拜先生 - 大人
- ah, master holbein. - my lord.
我还有一事须交由您去办
I have another commission for you.
克里维斯公爵已准许 由您
The duke of cleves has given you permission to.
为其女安画像 着您即刻启程
Paint his daughter anne you should leave at once.
阁下要务缠身
Your honor has so many pressing things.
却还有时间谈论绘画
And yet you have time to talk about a painting?
这并非平常画像 荷尔拜 先生
this is no ordinary painting, mr. holbein.
此事事关重大
A great many things hang upon it.
正因如此 无论那位女士真实相貌如何
To that effect, however you find the lady, whatever her actual appearance,
我都恳求您 至少把她画得赏心悦目
I pray you, use your art and give her at least a pleasing countenance.
即使她奇丑无比 也如此吗
even if she is as ugly as sin?
那她倒还不至那般不堪
I am fairly certain she is not so.
尽管如此 您还是希望我需要的话 美化她吗
but still, you wish me, if necessary, to lie?
显然一切艺术皆为美化 荷尔拜先生
surely all art is a lie, mr. holbein.
大人们
My lords,
鉴于法国国王与罗马皇帝签署了托莱多条约
Since the signing of the treaty of toledo between the french king and the emperor.
两国意图共侵我国
there have been vital and unavoidable signs.
已如箭在弦一触即发
of their mutual preparations for war against this realm.
我们知道在罗马教皇的煽动下 他们万分迫切
We know how much they have been urged on by the vicar of rome.
我们已获确切情报 他们在安特卫普及布洛涅两地
And now we hear competent reports of fleets gathering.
集结舰队 在荷兰也集结了一支军队
At antwerp and boulogne, and of an army in the netherlands.
另外
Furthermore,
法国和罗马的大使也都被召回
The french and imperial ambassadors have been recalled by their masters.
诸位 在剑拔弩张之当下 我们并未放松警惕
my lords, we have not been idle under such provocations.
我们已召集防卫军
Defense forces have been mustered and.
并在海岸边界设立烽火台戒备
Beacons set up along the coast for warning.
我们也已着手在英吉利海峡边筑建堡垒
Work has also begun building ancillary forts facing the english channel.
同时巩固了北面对苏格兰的边防线
In the north we've strengthened our borders against the scots.
陛下的战舰队也处于备战状态
And his majesty's fleet of warships has been provisioned.
没有国王的允许
And foreign vessels have been forbidden to.
任何外国船只不得离岸
Leave these shores without royal permission.
大人们 任谁都清楚那位主教大人
My lords, how can anyone doubt that the pope.
那位为祸人间的偶像
that pestilent idol,
是真理的敌人 是妄图篡权的掠夺者
That enemy of truth and usurpator of all princes,
如今正密谋破坏英格兰的信仰 掠夺我们的财富
Is now conspiring to corrupt england's religion and strip her of her wealth?
诸位 此时正是顺应民心的大好时机
My lords, at such a time it is good for me to be amongst my people.
我将巡视国内所有
I will visit all the places where the.
建筑防备工事之地
Barricades and defenses of the realm are Being built,
以此鼓舞军心 震慑敌军
For the encouragement of my troops and to the terror of my enemies.
陛下英明
My lord.
看来我们腹背受敌了 弗朗西斯爵士
it seems we are threatened from everywhere, sir francis.
苏格兰 西班牙 以及其他低地国家
Scotland. spain, the low countries.
人为刀俎 我为鱼肉啊
We are like a morsel among these choppers!
再告诉你件事吧 汤姆
I tell you something something else, tom.
据克伦威尔的探子回报
According to cromwell's agents,
两周前 珀尔主教离开罗马执行秘密任务
Just two weeks ago cardinal pole left rome on a secret mission.
我们要继续追捕他吗
shall we be after him again?
一旦得知他的藏身之所 即刻行动
as soon as we have more news of his whereabouts, we shall.
时刻准备着
Sharpen your knives.
- 公爵大人 - 大人
- your grace. - my lord.
- 可以私下聊聊吗 - 改天吧 大人 现在不行
- may we talk in private? - some time, my lord. not now.
荷尔拜先生送来了克里维斯的安的画像 陛下
mr. holbein has sent this portrait of anne of cleves, your majesty.
她挺惹人喜爱的
she is pleasing.
- 我们的大使和她正式见过面了吗 - 是的 陛下
- Has our ambassador been able to see her properly? - yes, your majesty.
约翰爵士来信中高度评价了公主的为人
Sir john has written to me in great praise of the princess' person.
他写道
He writes,
她无与伦比 更胜米兰公爵夫人一筹
"she is incomparable and excels the duchess of milan.
宛若灿烂的阳光胜过苍白的月光
as the golden sun excels the silver moon."
陛下 不知是否当讲
your majesty if I may?
同米兰公爵夫人的联姻已无可能
marriage to the duchess of milan is no longer an option.
由于法国同罗马帝国已联手对抗我国
Nor, since the french and the emperor are in league against us,
同法国联姻也已无望
Are any of the french women.
陛下已然腹背受敌
Your majesty is beset by enemies.
而同克里维斯的安联姻 能与新教国结成联盟
Marriage to anne of cleves would bring with it the.
在军事上和经济上的大力支持
Military and financial support of the protestant league.
怎么 怎么了
what? what is it?
敌船上挂着黑鹰旗帜
enemy ships flying the black eagle!
我看看
let me look!
是罗马帝国的船舰
It's imperial ships!
看在上帝的份上 点燃烽火台
for lord's sake, light the beacon!
快
Hurry!
快点
Light it!
看在上帝的份上
For god's sake!
天鹅宫 克里维斯 德国
Swan Castle Cleves, Germany.
威廉公爵
duke william,
陛下对您妹妹安的画像赞不绝口
His majesty is much taken by the portrait of your sister anne.
他敦促您派遣使节前往英格兰
He encourages you to send ambassadors to england to conclude negotiations,
商讨关于嫁妆及诸项事宜
Including the question of a suitable dowry, and so on.
我再说一次 贵国陛下实在操之过急
once again his majesty is premature.
但是 殿下
but surely, your highness…
我想国王应该亲自公开来访 屈膝跪地
I think the king should come to me publicly and on bended knee.
企求我妹之芳心 及寻求联盟之保护
To beg for my sister's hand and for the protection of the league.
无论如何 安已正式许配给了
In any case, anne is already promised, formally,
洛林公爵之子 我不知
To the duke of lorraine's son and I do not.
要如何出尔反尔 却又能保住尊严
See how I can break that promise and keep my honor.
殿下 若真如此 这实乃事出意外的坏消息
your highness, if true, this is most unexpected and unwelcome news.
这是因为你们从一开始就
That is because you expected from.
觊觎克利维斯的力量及我妹
The start to have your way with cleves.
但我这里
And my sister,
不是青楼妓院 我妹也不是妓女
but my country is not a brothel and my sister is not a whore.
既然如此
Well…
如果你们主子真心寻求结盟
if your master truly desires to have an alliance,
那么请他展示对我国的敬意
Then he must demonstrate his respect for my country…
并为得到我妹之童贞出个更高的价钱
And put a better price on my sister's virginity.
让开
make way!
让开 让开
Make way! make way!
- 给国王陛下的急件 - 先生
- message for the king! - sir.
这边走 孩子
Here, boy.
给陛下的急件
a message for his majesty.
陛下
Majesty.
是五港的看守托马斯·切尼的来信
"from sir thomas cheyney, warden, the cinque ports.
陛下 诸位枢密院大人
"your majesty, lords of council,
今晨在海峡边出现68艘罗马帝国船只
This morning we counted "68 imperial ships in the channel.
我派出两艘船前去探听虚实
"i sent out two ships, and,
随后我方船员登上罗马帝国的船只
"afterwards my boatmen were taken aboard the.
该船舰长对我船员礼遇有加
Imperial flagship "and shown every courtesy by the admiral.
他说他们的船队意欲驶往西班牙 而非英格兰
"he said his fleet was bound for spain and not england,
因而对我方或我海岸并无任何觊觎
"and that he meant no harm whatever "to us or our coast.
若不信可以查看
"if they doubted his word they had only to see.
其船只甚少武装装备
How poorly armed "his ships were, equipped more.
反而如普通商船一般
Like merchantmen,
他们负责输送罗马皇帝前往君士坦丁堡之航行所需物资
Their holds bursting with provisions for the emperor's voyage to constantinople."
陛下 帝国大使觐见
the imperial ambassador, your majesty.
我以为您已被召回
I thought you'd been recalled.
眼下的确是有一些传言 陛下
there was some talk, your majesty.
可我无意离开 我想也没有理由离开
But I had no desire to leave here nor did I think there was any cause.
没有理由
no cause?
贵国陛下已同法王
But your master and the french king.
缔结盟约与我为敌
had formed an alliance against me.
在罗马教廷的撺掇下
There appeared to be preparations for an invasion,
已磨刀霍霍 意图入侵
Encouraged by the vicar of rome.
陛下 我任职时间不短
your majesty, I've been in this job a long time.
知道什么时候该信 什么时候不该信
I know when to believe what I am told and When not to.
多数情况下 是不该采信的
which is most of the time.hmm…
尽管皇帝陛下公开的
Although the emperor publicly.
拥抱了法王 甚至亲手
Embraced the french king and even gave him the.
将颈上的金羊毛勋章赠与他
Order of the golden fleece from around his own neck,
可我主陛下依然憎恶他
He still continued to hate him.
众多敌国之中 我主陛下最惧土耳其人
More than any other enemy, my master fears the turks,
可法王仍与他们结盟
And yet the french are in league with them!
同为天主教帝国君主
How is such behavior.
这种行为岂能容谅
from another christian monarch to be forgiven?
- 那他们已不再结盟了么 - 尚未
- then they are no longer in alliance? - no.
但已面和心不合
The accord is already broken down.
如此一来 米兰公爵夫人
Which means that the duchess of milan is.
也可再次待选为陛下之妻
Once more available for your majesty's bed.
太迟了 查普维斯阁下
it's too late, mr. chapuys.
查普维斯阁下 说说看
Mr. Chapuys, tell me,
我又一次作为
Am I to be relieved that once more.
法王与贵主陛下博弈的一颗棋子
I've been used as a pawn in a game.
这回我能轻松了么
between your master and the french king?
此时此地 我告诉你
I tell you this, here and now.
我忍无可忍 查普维斯阁下
I've had enough, mr. chapuys!
我忍无可忍
I've had enough.
您可以退下了
You may leave.
两位阁下如此迅速折返 着实令人惊喜
I am surprised to see you back so soon, excellencies.
殿下 我们有喜讯禀报
we have good news, your highness.
喜从何来
how so?
陛下非令妹安妮不娶
His majesty is so desirous to marry your sister anne.
他宁可不要嫁妆
That he is willing to forfeit the requirements of a dowry.
他什么都不要吗
he wants nothing?
只要能与他的新娘速速成婚
only his new bride, in as short a time as possible.
陛下还会支付给殿下您
His majesty will also pay your highness a.
一笔数目可观的津贴
Considerable stipend.
以酬谢殿下您撮合陛下与新教联盟
for introducing him to the league.
此外
however,
我们知晓令妹
We recall that your sister is already.
已许给了洛林公爵之子
Promised to the son of the duke of lorraine.
的确如此
ah, yes.
那确是一大阻碍
That was indeed a great obstacle.
然而 近期经过考证
However, on closer consideration,
我们发觉婚约尚未获准
We have discovered that the contract was never ratified,
因为不受法律或其他形式的约束
And so is not binding in law or any other way.
那么令妹仍可许给国王
so your sister is free to marry the king?
我将派遣使臣前往英国定下婚约
I will send my ambassadors to england to conclude the negotiations.
谢谢了 先生们
Thank you, gentlemen.
这是什么
What's this?
克伦威尔的探子
Cromwell's agents.
还是截到了珀尔主教的信
finally intercepted a letter from cardinal pole.
是送往罗马的途中截获的
It was on its way to rome.
- 我设法破译了它 - 我能看看吗
- I have managed to decode it. - may I see?
冯·瓦尔德巴主教敬启
"to cardinal von waldburg.
本该前往巴黎面见弗朗西斯国王
"supposed to travel to paris to meet king francis.
此前已去信
"have already written,
告知罗马帝国皇帝陛下
Telling him I found the emperor.
十分支持我此项使命
"very sympathetic to my mission.
可我担心并非如此
"but fear it is not so.
较亨利国王而言 罗马帝国皇帝更忌惮土耳其
"the emperor fears the turk more than king henry,
故此我确信陛下不会对亨利国王采取行动
"so believe he will not act against him.
因此行程延期
"so postponed journey.
将先去往教廷辖区卡彭特拉斯
"will go instead "to papal city of carpentras.
原地待教皇陛下之命
Await further instruction from his holiness."
去过卡彭特拉斯吗
have you ever been to carpentras?
没有
no.
可我迫不及待
But I'm dying to go.
- 大人 萨福克公爵到 - 公爵大人
- the duke of suffolk, my lord. - your grace.
贵人到访不胜荣幸
To what do I owe this honor?
我来此恭贺您
I'm here to congratulate you.
我知道国王已封您为何福特伯爵
I understand the king has made you earl of hertford.
我想也到了摒除异议
And I believe it is time to.
尽释前嫌的时候
patch up our past quarrels and differences.
应该多多商讨而非争论
There are better quarrels to be had.
很高兴与大人意见一致
I am happy to agree with your grace.
喝一点
Drink?
劳驾
please.
请坐
我奉王命去加来面见公主
I am commanded to meet the princess at calais.
太多事悬于这桩婚事 不是吗
A great many things hang upon this marriage, do they not?
比方说 国王的幸福
the king's happiness, for one.
还有克伦威尔大人的威信
And my lord cromwell's reputation.
倘若她因某些原因 有甚闪失 那可太遗憾了
what a pity if all should go awry for some reason.
我将对国王深感同情
I would have pity for the king.
对另一方面呢
but on the other hand?
干杯
Salut.
salut.
那么他真要娶信奉路德教的异教徒吗
so he is marrying a lutheran heretic?
- 看来如此 - 那我谁也不嫁
- so it seems. - and I shall marry no one!
- 小姐 我 - 不 我宁可如此
- my lady, i… - no. I prefer it.
你想我会愿意嫁给公爵的兄弟
Do you suppose I would like to be married off to the duke's brother,
或者他的什么异教徒表亲吗
Or some heretic cousin of his?
我宁可住进修道院
I would prefer to live in a nunnery!
真不知道国王怎么了
I do not know what to think of the king.
烧死了个路德教徒 再娶个路德教徒
He burns one lutheran, and then marries another!
那么 既然是上帝安排的
Well, if god so wills it,
她也许会淹死在海上
she might drown at sea!
切克斯城堡 加来 英属法国领地
Chequers, Calais English Occupied France.
先生们
gentlemen,
值此良辰吉日 我们欢迎各位莅临加来
We bid you welcome to calais on this most auspicious occasion.
谢谢
danke.
请允许我介绍萨福克公爵殿下
may I present to you his grace, the duke of suffolk.
大人 十分荣幸
your grace. an honor.
我叫霍斯顿
I am Herr Hoghesten,
这位是奥列斯卡伯爵
and this is Count Olisleger,
您好
hallo.
安妮公主殿下 即刻驾到 精诚所至 上帝啊
Her highness, princess anne, after a long time my god!
公主殿下
your highness.
日安 公爵大人
good day, your grace.
气候条件恶劣
I'm afraid the bad weather.
恐怕要耽搁几日航程
will prevent our sailing for a few days.
我理解
I understand.
公爵大人能否
Perhaps your grace could, uh,
拨冗为我介绍一下英国的进餐礼仪
Help me to explain how the english are eating?
义不容辞
of course.
并且告诉我国王陛下的一些爱好吗
and maybe show me something the king likes to do?
陛下喜好玩牌九还有赌博
his majesty likes to play cards and gamble.
您玩吗
Do you play?
噢 不会
oh, no.
我国只有男子赌牌九
I think only the men play the cards in my country, ja?
赌博不是不好的么
is it not bad to gamble?
要是输得起就没问题
not if you can afford to lose.
我们来玩皮克牌
we'll play piquet.
- 一点都不难学 - 太好了
- It's not hard to learn. - that is good.
扑克牌有四种花色
there are four suits of cards comme ca.
分别是 黑桃 梅花 方块 还有红心
spades, clubs, diamonds and hearts.
红心 你喜欢玩弄感情
hearts? you play with hearts?
有时候吧
sometimes.
这里我们有王牌 国王 王后和杰克
And here we have aces, kings, queens and knaves.
整个宫廷都在这儿了 是吧
ah! then all the court is here.
国王总是赢牌吗
does the king always win?
陛下不喜欢输
his majesty does not like losing.
他们是怎么跟您说国王的
What have they told you about the king?
怎么了
why?
有什么是我该知道的吗
What is it I should know?
- 你是弗朗西斯·布莱恩吗 - 可以带我们去见红衣主教吗
- you're francis bryan? - you can take us to the cardinal?
是的 快来 他和我们在一起
si. yes. come quickly. he is with us.
那杂种在哪
where is the bastard?
抱歉 先生
Sorry, signor.
愿主保佑
e prego.
追随上帝的指引 孩子
Go with god, my sons.
我们永远也抓不到他
we'll never catch him.
纯属浪费时间
A waste of time.
也许不是
perhaps not.
亲爱的
o dulcis…
仁慈的主啊 圣母玛利亚之子 请怜悯我们
O pie, o jesu fili mariae; miserere mei…
圣母玛利亚请保佑我们
Holy Mary Pray for us.
引渡我躲过敌人的追捕
and deliver me from my enemies.
阿门
Amen.
- 你没看见她的脸 - 没有 陛下
- you didn't see her face? - no, your majesty.
但她打牌时和气可爱
But she plays cards as pleasantly and with as.
高雅端庄的姿态一如我见过的任何贵族女子
Good a grace as ever in my life I saw any noble woman.
她已经到了罗切斯特市
she's come to rochester.
我将在三日后见她
I'm due to meet her in three days time.
告诉你吧 我迫不及待地要见她
I tell you, I'm more impatient than ever to see her.
弗朗西斯·布莱恩爵士进展如何
What of sir francis bryan?
他和托马斯·西摩爵士已经到了卡朋特拉斯
he and sir thomas seymour are arrived in carpentras,
珀尔主教应该是藏在那儿
Where cardinal pole is supposed to be hiding.
显然他开始害怕被暗杀
It appears he has grown fearful of assassination.
他应当日此
he has every right to be so.
我发誓
I swear,
那人该被剥皮 然后我要把他的皮当衬衫穿
That man should be flayed alive and I should wear his skin as a shirt!
他终有一天会后悔 容许教皇利用他来威胁我
He will rue the day he allowed the pope to use him to threaten me.
跟你说 我实在等不了了
I tell you, I cannot abide this waiting!
我等的够久了
It's been a long time.
我需要爱情的浇灌
I need to nourish love!
- 我理解 - 你能吗
- I can understand. - can you?
我想要得到这个女人
I want to possess this woman…
但至今仍未见过她
And I haven't even seen her!
对我来说 她完全是个陌生人
She's a complete stranger to me.
如果我不能
What if I can't…
如果您不能 怎样
what if you can't… what?
来人
groom!
陛下
majesty.
把马师叫来 我即刻动身去往罗切斯特市 快去
fetch the master of the horse. I leave for rochester immediately. go!
让路
make way!
下马
Dismount!
去通报小姐 一位绅士前来见她 带来了新年礼物
Tell the lady a gentleman has come to see her bearing a new year's gift.
快去
Go.
夫人
Madam.
我来此欢迎您来到我国
I'm here to welcome you to my realm.
相信您到访伦敦之前
I trust you are comfortable here.
会在此地过的十分愉快
before your Journey to london.
谢谢您 陛下
thank you, your majesty.
稍后见
I will see you anon.
我该从公爵那儿多学点的
I should have taken more lessons from the Duke.
英格兰的礼仪同我国真是大有不同
English manners are very different from ours!
我一点不喜欢她
I like her not!
听明白吗
Do you understand me?
我不喜欢她
I like her not!!
召开政务会议
Call a meeting of the council.
看起来王公贵族的婚姻比贫民的更悲惨
It seems that princes in marriage suffer more than poor men,
因为他们只能照单全收
Since they have to take what is brought to them,
而贫民却能自由的选择
While poor men are at liberty to choose.
关于克里维斯的安 我被骗了
I have been deceived about anne of cleves.
她同你们报告的截然不同
She is nothing like what was reported to me.
截然不同 她看着就像匹马
Nothing! she looks like a horse!!!
一匹佛兰德斯母马
A flanders mare!
陛下应该还记得约翰爵士是怎么描述她的吧
Your majesty will remember that it was sir john who described her.
- 长得就像 - 臣从未亲眼见过她 错不在臣
- As being like…- I never saw her properly which was not my fault.
我已竭尽全力 尽忠职守
I carried out my commission as best I could.
而且我告诉过你 我对女人所知甚少
And I told you I was no good with women.
克伦威尔大人
my lord cromwell.
您是在否认 曾对我吹嘘过她的美丽
Do you deny that you spoke to me of her beauty,
声称她会是我称心如意的新娘
Of the desirability of my marriage to her?
我不否认 陛下
no, your majesty.
如果我因为错误的报告而误导了陛下和政务院
And if I have misled your majesty and his council by.
我深感遗憾
Commendations based on false reports, then I am truly sorry for it.
早知如此 她是绝不会被带到这里
if I had known what I know now, she would never have been brought here!
怎么补救 克伦威尔大人
What remedy, mr. cromwell?
陛下 臣不得不说 别无他法
your majesty, I have to say that there is none.
不可能
that's hardly the case.
克里维斯之事一开始就由您接手的
You've been following the cleves agenda from the beginning.
继续
go on.
如今罗马帝国皇帝已是法国国王的贵客
today the emperor is the guest of the king of france.
他们已重新结盟
They have renewed their alliance.
如果我们现在拒绝德国的联姻
If we now reject our german allies,
英国将陷于孤立无援之地
Then england will remain alone and friendless,
任由法国国王和教皇的摆布
And at the mercy of the king and emperor.
陛下 如果您现在解除婚约
Your majesty, if you break this marriage contract now,
恐怕威廉公爵本人都会报复我们
You risk the possibility that even of duke William himself might retaliate against us.
我很抱歉陛下对此事不甚满意
I'm…I'm sorry that your majesty has no better content.
这事没有处理好 克伦威尔先生
I am not well handled, mr. cromwell.
陛下
Your majesty.
小姐
my lady.
欢迎您的到来 这一切都属于您
I'm here to welcome you to what is yours.
陛下您真是十分慷慨 我很愉快
your majesty is very gracious and I am very happy.
我的女儿们
My daughters.
玛丽公主
The princess mary.
夫人
madam.
伊丽莎白公主
the princess elizabeth.
给您的 我觉得这花很漂亮
for you. I think they're pretty.
谢谢您 公主 您也很漂亮
thank you, princess. I think you are pretty, too.
我会好好疼爱她们俩的
I shall love them both.
我不喜欢她
I like her not.
但看来陛下必须得娶她
but it seems that your majesty must marry her.
谁说我必须娶她了 克伦威尔吗
who says I must? cromwell?
我自有律师团在处理此事
I have my lawyers working on it.
有两个办法解除婚约
The betrothal can be prevent on two grants.
要么就是德国使节
Either the german envoys fail to bring a.
没有将公爵授予的
Commission from the duke authorizing them to conclude the.
婚姻合法判决书送到
Legalities of the marriage.
要么就是他们不能提供公主的
or they can't provide written.
上一桩婚约被正式撤销的书面证据
Evidence that her previous betrothal was formally revoked.
两者取其一 我就能摆脱这桩婚事了
Either way, I can get out of it.
衷心希望陛下您能如愿
I wish with all my heart that your majesty is successful.
在我看来 克伦威尔大人
It seems to me that my lord cromwell is.
十分强调这事完全没有回转的余地
Too keen to stress the lack of any remedy.
这桩婚事是他的主意
the marriage was his idea.
本还有其他候选人
There were other candidates.
比如米兰的公爵夫人
The duchess of milan is supposed to.
她可是天下无双的美人啊
Be the most desirable woman in the world!
而不是这个
Instead of which…
也许 在这件事上
perhaps, in this matter,
克伦威尔大人有点过分干预了吧
my lord cromwell has overreached himself?
也许吧
perhaps.
上帝啊
Oh, god!
如果不能挽回的话 我就只能套上这副绳索了
If there is no remedy, I must put my neck into this yoke!
大人
my lord!
抱歉 克伦威尔大人
I'm sorry, lord cromwell.
我没看到您 我
I didn't see you. i…
我正和上帝交谈
I was talking to god.
但显然 先生 您得去教堂才能祷告
but surely, sir, you have to go to church for that?
你对我们的改革一无所知吗
do you understand nothing of our reforms?
上帝不仅在教堂 他无所不在
God is not just in church. he is everywhere.
我们不需要牧师为我们祷告
We do not need priests to speak for us.
我们可以自行和他沟通 他会听到的
We can speak to him ourselves, and he will listen.
不必非要有排钟 圣经和蜡烛
There's no need for bells and books and candles.
只要有灵魂就够了
All you need is your soul.
退下吧 再好好想想
Now go away and think.
等等
Wait.
今天是显灵节宴会
today is the feast of the epiphany.
也是我大婚之日
And my wedding day.
那么 还是没有合法的解决途径吗
So there was no legal remedy?
恐怕是找不着了 陛下
none that it was possible to discover, your majesty.
这事儿你没有办好
I am not well handled.
我想只要您更深入了解她
I think when your majesty gets to know the lady better…
我不要深入了解她 克伦威尔先生
I don't want to know the lady better, mr. cromwell!
一想到这件事就让我恶心
The notion of it revolts me.
大人 如果不是为了江山社稷
My lord, if it were not to satisfy the world, and my realm,
我是绝不会做今天我必须做的事
I would not do what I must do this day for no earthly thing!
可以就寝了吗
shall we to bed?
是的 陛下
your majesty.
陛下
Your majesty.
陛下觉得王后怎么样
How does your majesty like the queen?
很显然 大人 我以前不怎喜欢她
Surely, my lord, I didn't like her very much before.
现在更加讨厌她
and I like her much worse now!
她一点都不美好 她身上一股邪恶的味道
She is nothing fair and she has evil smells about her!
从她松弛的胸部及其他表征
And I know she's no maid.
我就可以看出她根本不是处女
because of the looseness of her breasts and other tokens.
因此我没这个意愿也没这个勇气去继续探究
So I had neither the will nor the courage to prove the rest.
对令人生厌的气味下我没一点性趣
I have no appetite for unpleasant airs.
我让她来时什么样就是什么样
I left her as good a maid as I found her!
现在 大人 退下吧
And now, my lord, leave me.
我很忙
I'm very busy.
陛下
your majesty.
- 亲爱的 - 我睡不着
- sweetheart. - I couldn't sleep.
- 谁在那儿 - 没人 回你床上去
- Who is there? - no one. go back to bed.
我过会儿可以来陪你吗
Shall I come to you later?
如果你还是我以前亲爱的查尔斯
if you could still be my sweet charles.
我和从前一样
I am as good as I may be.
你要对此深信不疑
And you must take me as I am.
我爱你 凯瑟琳
I love you, catherine.
我已经把脓血从您的伤口抽出来了
I have drained the pus from your majesty's wound.
您应该不会再忍受疼痛了 感谢上帝
Your majesty should feel no more pain, thanks be to god.
恕我冒昧 您还有其他烦心事儿吗
Forgive me, but is your majesty troubled by other things?
我不能和安女士圆房
I have been unable to consummate my marriage with the lady anne.
我觉得她的身体有点 病弱欠佳
I find her body in such a sort, disordered and indisposed,
无法激起我的一丝性欲
That it doesn't excite me or provoke any lust in me.
您就没听过一点谣传么
Have you heard any rumors of it?
一点儿也没 陛下
none at all, your majesty.
这不是我能力方面的问题
it is not anything to do with my virility.
实际上在这些夜晚我曾有过两次射精
Indeed these last nights I have had duas pollutiones nocturnas in somno.
两次射精
two nocturnal emissions.
你看
you see,
我知道我跟谁都能行房
I know myself perfectly able to perform.
唯独跟她不行
The act with others, just not with her.
和她
With her,
我根本没欲望做夫妻之间该做的事情
I have no appetite to do what a man should do to his wife.
- 克伦威尔大人 - 陛下
- my lord cromwell? - your majesty.
- 可以和您单独谈谈吗 - 单独
- May we speak alone? - alone?
可以 当然
Oh, ja. of course.
大人
My lord?
夫人 恕我冒昧 我来是为一件棘手的问题
madam, I have come on a delicate matter. forgive me.
我
I…
必须警告您 切勿惹恼国王
Must warn you against antagonizing the king.
请您谨记 尽最大努力
I must remind you of the expediency of doing.
顺应陛下的意思
Your utmost to make yourself agreeable to him.
先生 我都不知道是哪里冒犯了国王
sir, I am not sure how I have given his majesty offence.
您与国王的婚姻美满
it is in your interest, and in mine,
对您对我都有利
To make your marriage to the king a success.
如果 您能很快怀上孩子的话
If, for example, you were to find yourself quick with child…
很抱歉要跟您讨论这等私事
I'm sorry to talk of such intimate.
但您作为一国之母
Matters but you are the queen of england.
您就不再有私事了
You have nothing private anymore.
国王不碰我的话
How am I to become quick with child.
我又怎么很快怀上孩子呢
when the king leaves me a maid?
我不是圣母玛利亚
I am not the virgin mary!
既然您说 我没有私事了
And since you say me I am nothing.
那么我要告诉您 这事一点不令人愉快
Private then I say you it is not all pleasing.
我会竭尽所能讨国王欢心
I will do anything the king wants.
但有时
But sometimes…
他腿上的伤口会恶化 渗出脓血
The sore on his leg is bad. It oozes blood and pus.
而且有气味
And It smells.
恶臭难忍
It stinks!
恶臭 您明白吗
It smells, ja. you understand?
对不起 大人
Now, I am sorry, my lord.
我会继续努力讨国王欢心
I will go on doing all that I can to make myself agreeable to his majesty,
他对我始终那么和蔼友善
Who is always gracious and kind to me.
陛下
your majesty.
夫人 您觉得国王怎样
madam, how do you find the king?
怎么了 布莱恩女士 他很和蔼亲切
why, he is most kind and solicitous, lady bryan.
他上床时 他会吻我 再牵着我的手
When he comes to bed he kisses me, ja, e takes my hand.
对我说 晚安 爱人
and bids me, "good night, sweetheart."
然后在早上 他会再次吻我
Then in the morning he kisses me again.
并说声 再会 亲爱的
and says, "farewell, darling."
夫人 我们都希望您能尽快怀上孩子
my lady, we all hope you will be with child soon.
我很清楚我做不到
I know very well I am not.
您怎么会知道你不行呢
but how do you know you are not?
我再清楚不过了 我不会的
I know it well. I am not.
我想陛下您还是个处女
I think your majesty is a maid still.
他必须把他那物件放进您身体 搅动一下
He must put his member inside you and stir it,
否则我们将不会有约克公爵
Or else we shall not have a duke of york,
这可是万众期待的啊
which all this realm desires.
我很满足了 布莱恩女士
I am contented, lady bryan!
我得到了我所希望的 国王的最多的关怀
I receive as much of the king's attentions as I wish.
我不知道还能要求什么了
I know no more!
布莱恩女士
Lady bryan?
是 陛下
yes, your majesty?
如果我不能讨国王欢心
if I cannot please the king…
他会杀了我吗
Will he kill me?